[music]
>> I don't know if you've read this. It's
on all the best seller lists. Don't
bother if you haven't. It's so silly. It
starts with someone being killed in one
of the corridors here at the Louvre in
Paris.
This chap is the keeper of an ancient
secret and if he dies, the ancient
secret dies with him. So, he crawls
along the long corridor and seeks out
the most famous painting in the Louvre.
And there, he scrolls a secret message
on the glass that protects the Mona
Lisa.
Now, the Mona Lisa has long been a
magnet for mystery addicts and
fruitcakes.
You want mysteries? She's got loads of
them.
The mystery of her elusive identity, the
mystery of her elusive smile.
It's even been said she's a projected
self-portrait of Leonardo as a
cross-dresser.
Even her eyebrows are mysterious. Why
hasn't she got any?
But there is one mystery concerning the
Mona Lisa that can actually be solved
and we're going to do it in this film.
It's perhaps the deepest mystery of all
and that is why, out of all the
countless old masters gathered in all
our museums, why did this particular one
become the most famous painting in the
world? Now, that's a mystery worth
solving.
The Mona Lisa is 500 years old.
She was painted in Florence in around
1503.
In Paris, they've recently been
celebrating her birthday.
500 years old. It's a good age.
But the first thing to grasp about the
Mona Lisa's ridiculous fame is that it's
rather new.
For 300 years after she was painted, the
Mona Lisa was almost entirely unknown.
Just a handful of people in history had
ever seen her or even heard of her.
She only started to become famous about
150 years ago and really, really famous,
this famous in the 20th century. So, her
fame is rather new.
So, by the way, is the fame of her
creator Leonardo da Vinci.
Today, we think of Leonardo as the
greatest genius of the Renaissance,
scientist, mathematician, anatomist,
the man who not only painted the Mona
Lisa, but who also invented flying
machines, submarines, and bicycles.
And it's just not true. I'm not saying
that Leonardo didn't vaguely imagine
some of those things, but I am saying
that he never actually built any of
them. Leonardo almost discovered lots of
things, but only almost. His tragedy is
that he never went the final mile, the
bit that counts.
Well, Leonardo was not that celebrated.
Uh um one of the problem is that
Leonardo did not paint very much.
Whereas Raphael was on a production
line, you know, one after the other. Um
Michelangelo uh
did the whole ceiling after all or all
walls of the Sistine Chapel, you know,
you know,
huge project in 4 years, which is what
apparently uh you know, it took Leonardo
to paint, you know, this tiny portrait.
Um so, if you wanted to, you know, lots
of work, you were not going to ask him.
You know that famous drawing that people
always say is him, the old man with a
big biblical beard and the all-seeing
eyes?
Well, there's no actual evidence it's
Leonardo, just our wishful thinking
because this old man with the big beard
reminds us of some great biblical
leader, doesn't he? Moses, perhaps, or
even God.
So, the next thing to get clear in our
minds is that Leonardo da Vinci is
chiefly like this, a work of fiction.
And before we tiptoe any further into
the conceptual quagmire that is the
mystery of the Mona Lisa, I think we
need to find out a tad more about the
real Leonardo.
>> [music]
[music]
>> Olives.
They're everywhere on this hill.
In fact, just about the only thing
that's up here
is olive groves.
We're about 2 km out [music] of Vinci,
little Tuscan town of Vinci, place
called Anchiano.
About 20 miles out of Florence.
And this
simple
little Tuscan
hill house
is the house
in which Leonardo da Vinci was born
in 1452. [music]
His father was a notary, a lawyer called
Ser Piero da Vinci.
And his mother, all we know about her is
that she was called Caterina. And
Leonardo
>> [music]
>> was their illegitimate son.
Leonardo's father bought this house from
the friars that used to own it. He was
working for them as a lawyer.
And it's hardly changed since then.
It's just two very basic little rooms,
really.
Lovingly preserved in their original
state of decrepitude.
But look at this.
Just above the window on the front.
A lion wearing a helmet. That's the coat
of arms of the da Vinci family.
Original fireplace.
Leonardo.
Ghastly likeness, I think.
Coat of arms again.
It's rather spooky feeling, actually.
It's such a humble place
for such a big brain to have been born.
Leonardo's artistic career is so
frustrating. He's always starting things
and never finishing them.
He spent the first 30 years of his life
in Florence, yet all he had to show for
all this time was a couple of pictures.
One of them is this gorgeous [music]
portrait of Ginevra de Benci.
She's rather glum. Why?
In Italian, Ginevra means juniper. So,
the halo of juniper around her head is a
coded clue to her identity.
From the start, Leonardo could make his
women feel mysterious.
Here's an early Madonna and Child that
hangs in the Hermitage in Russia.
What a ghastly multi-pounded Jesus. Look
at the size of him.
I don't like her expression, either.
It looks forced to me.
Say cheese. Cheese.
These early experiments with different
women's expressions had such mixed
results that Leonardo soon settled on
one he knew he could rely on, an
expression he always used. You know it
already. It's that mysterious smile
playing on a woman's lips.
Whether they're the Virgin Mary or a
girl off the street, Leonardo began
giving his women the same look.
The Mona Lisa's mysterious smile was an
expression he was churning out.
>> [music]
[music]
>> For the next 20 years, Leonardo worked
in Milan as the in-house genius for the
local dukes, starting lots of things,
finishing none of them,
except this,
The Last Supper,
the famous masterpiece that's been
falling off the wall ever since he
painted it because the technique he used
was so lousy.
After 20 years in Milan, he returned to
Florence.
He was already in his 50s when a
commission came his way that would
finally lead to his most famous
achievement,
a portrait of a plumpish Florentine
merchant's wife named Lisa Gherardini.
There are lots of extraordinary
surprises in the story of the Mona Lisa,
but perhaps the earliest of them is that
that story begins here in this grim
little Florentine street, called the Via
della Stufa.
Now, this is the street in which Lisa
Gherardini, who is traditionally thought
to have been the Florentine lady who
posed for the Mona Lisa, actually lived.
She was married to a Florentine cloth
merchant called Francesco del Giocondo,
and that explains why in France she's
known as La Gioconde, why in Italy they
call her La Gioconda, and why, rather
confusingly, the rest of us call her
Mona Lisa, Madonna Lisa. It's what
everybody would have said to her.
Madonna Lisa becomes Mona Lisa.
Thus, in this grim little Florentine
street, populated these days chiefly by
Florentine lowlife, the great legend of
the Mona Lisa was born.
For some reason, Leonardo never handed
over the Mona Lisa to Francesco del
Giocondo and his wife. Probably because
he never considered her finished. He was
such a fiddler.
Leonardo's career was now on the slide.
In Italy, he was out of fashion, and his
reputation for not finishing things
preceded him wherever he wandered.
Internationally, what fame he had was
due entirely to his much copied comic
grotesques of ugly old men and big-nosed
Jews. They're rather racist, really.
It was the French king Francois I
who saved Leonardo by taking him in when
no one else would have him.
Francois invited the 64-year-old
multitasker to work for him in France in
the Chateau at Amboise on the Loire.
Leonardo brought the Mona Lisa with him,
and no doubt fiddled with her some more.
When he died here 3 years later in 1519,
the Mona Lisa entered the French royal
collection, and to all intents and
purposes, disappeared for 300 years.
And then, the uh
um first great break for the Mona Lisa,
the first great career move, as I would
put it, uh the French Revolution.
Um what what the French Revolution does,
apart from minor things like abolishing
the monarchy and and so on, is to
transform the Louvre into a museum. So,
at least she's now gone from, you know,
semi-obscurity
to a proper proper place.
Another thing is Napoleon.
Napoleon took a shine to many women, and
one of these was Mona Lisa, and indeed,
for I think 4 years, the Mona Lisa was
removed from public viewing and was in
Napoleon's bedroom. Um and then it was
put back in the Louvre, um and has
remained there ever ever since.
>> [music]
>> You know, before Napoleon carried the
Mona Lisa away to his bedroom, hardly
anyone had seen her, and no one thought
of her as this figure of mystery and
allure.
She was a portrait by Leonardo, and
that's it. But now that she was in the
Louvre, and the Louvre was open to the
public, she was ready to fall into the
clutches of the public imagination.
And so, her ludicrous journey to global
fame could finally begin. Hang on to
your hats, because we're taking you on
it.
When we left you, the Mona Lisa had just
got to the Louvre, and people could
finally see what she looked like.
They liked what they saw, but had
trouble agreeing on what it was. Then,
as now, everyone found something
different in the Mona Lisa.
In the middle of the 19th century,
some intellectuals and writers begin to
discuss the Mona Lisa as the most
formidable
um example of the femme fatale.
This is when the smile becomes
mysterious and enigmatic.
There's no mention of an enigmatic smile
with with the Mona Lisa. I mean,
basically, until about 1850, Mona Lisa
is a cheerful housewife. From 1850
onwards, she is a castrating female.
You won't believe some of the silly
things that began to be written about
her by the feverish blokes of the 19th
century.
Let me read you something here. It's
perhaps the most famous passage ever
written about the Mona Lisa by an
eccentric English epicurean called
Walter Pater, who was obsessed with her.
"She is older than the rocks among which
she sits," he gushed in 1873.
"Like the vampire, she's been dead many
times and learned the secrets of the
grave and been a diver in deep seas."
And it just goes on and on. I mean, this
isn't art history, this is stalking. The
Mona Lisa had begun to drive men mad.
>> [music]
>> Thus, the Mona Lisa entered the creative
imagination of the 19th century, where
she would have stayed famous among
writers and art critics, and that's
about it, if something else hadn't
happened. Something sensational.
Something that turned her into a public
celebrity.
Well, of course, you needed an event.
You needed a photo opportunity. And that
occurred in the shape of an Italian
workman, um Vincenzo Peruggia, who stole
the painting in August 1911, and kept it
for 2 years in his bedsit, not far from
the Louvre, near the stove. The Mona
Lisa is a piece of wood, so you can
imagine the
possibility, the terrible possibilities.
And that made the world press.
>> [music]
>> Every day for 3-4 weeks,
there was something about the Mona Lisa.
The police can't find it. The security
of the Louvre is terrible. The director
of the Department of Paintings had to
resign. You know, it was became a sort
of cause célèbre, so people could see
the Mona Lisa nearly every day
as they were having their breakfast.
So, why would anyone be so stupid as to
steal the Mona Lisa?
Various conspiracy theories were aired
at the time, and indeed, people have
been airing them ever since. The
likeliest answer is that the entire mad
plot was the handywork of an Argentinian
forger called Eduardo de Valfierno.
Valfierno's crazy idea was to produce a
handful, perhaps six or seven copies of
the Mona Lisa while he had it in his
hands, and then to sell these copies on
to some very, very gullible American
millionaires.
Now, this has never been proved. What's
certain is that if you were a very
gullible American millionaire, you would
hardly have popped up afterwards and
said, "Yes, I bought one of these." And
undoubtedly, there were these very
special copies floating around the
European art world after the theft.
However, once Valfierno had done his
dirty deed and produced his copies, he
no longer had any real need for the
painting itself. So, he handed it back
to his accomplice, Peruggia, and
Peruggia was stuck with the Mona Lisa, a
painting that the whole world was
looking for.
What was he going to do with it?
>> [music]
>> Peruggia must have realized that the
painting was far too hot to do anything
with in France. So, he came back here to
Italy, and he holed up in this hotel in
Florence, which used to be called the
Tripoli Italia, but which, not
surprisingly, has now changed its name
to the Gioconda.
Because it's in this hotel that the
great lost painting was finally found.
Peruggia contacted a Florentine antique
dealer called Alfredo Geri and offered
to sell him the Mona Lisa for half a
million lira.
Inevitably, Geri
contacted the Italian police. 3 days
later, they came here to the hotel and
arrested Vincenzo Peruggia.
When they got inside Peruggia's room,
they found the Mona Lisa tucked away in
a suitcase underneath his bed.
And when they asked him why he'd stolen
her, Peruggia replied that it was an act
of patriotism all along.
All he'd ever really wanted to do was to
ensure that the great Florentine beauty
was returned to her rightful home.
Peruggia was sent down for a year for
stealing the Mona Lisa, which doesn't
seem very much, does it?
But one thing's certain, no matter how
famous the Mona Lisa was before Peruggia
and his cronies stole her from the
Louvre, this prior fame was as nothing
compared with the enormous global
notoriety that the picture acquired once
all those newspapers and all those
columns had stopped writing about the
great theft of the Mona Lisa.
And so, our plump Florentine housewife
finally became an international
celebrity at the age of 400. Because of
the robbery, everyone now knew what she
looked like, and everyone wanted to know
more [music] about her.
In 1919, the notorious Dada artist
Marcel Duchamp proved she'd really
arrived by taking the mickey out of her,
giving her a mustache and a goatee,
and adding the letters [music]
L.H.O.O.Q.
In French, a naughty pun, which means
she's got a hot ass, [music] or as we
might perhaps say today, a hot booty.
There's not any single moment where Lisa
becomes the world's most famous
painting. There are building blocks,
there are stepping stones.
So, being in Paris is an important
thing. Being painted by a Renaissance
genius is quite important. Being a femme
fatale or being described as a
castrating woman
would do you no harm. Being stolen was a
great stroke of luck.
Being mocked by futurist and avant-garde
artist was also very important. And
being regularly exploited by the
advertising industry in order to sell
everything from
fridge magnets, hotels,
flights,
and condoms even.
You know, all that
is is a tremendous asset for for a girl.
I can't face going into detail about the
subsequent growth of the Mona Lisa tat
industry. It's too horrible to witness.
Instead, let's just visit the house of
the world's biggest hoarder of Mona Lisa
memorabilia and savor some of the
highlights of his collection.
My house has become somewhat of a Mona
Lisa museum, a shrine, if you like.
I have gathered together some of the
most beautiful items I have in my
collection.
Like this wonderful photo mosaic here.
Although the reflection is a bit
irritating.
These magnificent cushions.
These ceramic tiles from China.
And this American.
It's called the giggling Mona Lisa.
And this Persian rug. It's a bit
amateurish, but still, it's magnificent.
>> [music]
>> And this is something I made myself.
It's based on William Tell, but as you
can see,
the arrow has missed its target.
>> [music]
>> Once you're famous for being famous, all
you can really do is become more famous
still. It's the golden rule of modern
celebrity.
And the case of Lisa Gherardini proves
it so clearly.
So, that's cleared up the mystery of how
the Mona Lisa got famous.
What it doesn't explain is how she ever
managed to be obscure in the first
place.
How can a painting as wonderful as this
ever be obscure?
Go on, forget everything [music] you've
ever heard about her. Forget the teacups
and the posters. Just go and look at her
properly.
You'll enjoy it.
There are a million stories in the world
of art.
This has been just one of them.